<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[syntactic umami]]></title>
  <link href="http://eaud.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://eaud.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-16T22:44:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://eaud.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Derek Mueller]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5-Minute Guide: How to Begin Using D3.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://eaud.github.io/blog/2015/12/16/how-to-begin-using-d3/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-16T22:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://eaud.github.io/blog/2015/12/16/how-to-begin-using-d3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i.stack.imgur.com/JPYn9.gif" alt="D3 visualization from " />
source: <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/18056678/hiding-text-elements-in-d3-chord-diagram">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/18056678/hiding-text-elements-in-d3-chord-diagram</a></p>

<h3>What is D3.js?</h3>

<h6>R2D-who? More like D3, <em>honey.</em></h6>

<p>You&rsquo;ve probably heard about D3 or seen D3 in action before - if you&rsquo;ve ever seen any awesome information graphic in the New York Times in recent years&hellip; probably D3. Maybe you arrived here because you need to make an infographic, maybe you.  In any case you&rsquo;re embarking on an important next step in information storytelling.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, it&rsquo;s basically a fact that you&rsquo;ve had to make some sort of chart, graph, or information visual in your life.  Perhaps you used Excel or Powerpoint or Adobe Creative or even CSS (ok, I see you!). No matter your method, if you&rsquo;ve ever gone about sharing it, you have probably encountered the common dilemma that data today changes.  Fast.  By the time you&rsquo;ve made your static visual and posted it on your blog, it&rsquo;s already out of date.</p>

<p>Enter <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3.js</a> - a Javascript library* that provides methods for rendering dynamic data visualization in browser through an intricate dance of HTML, CSS, and the data you want to visualize.</p>

<p>*(a Javascript library, in case that&rsquo;s an unfamiliar term, is essentially a set of extra methods that have been pre-made for you out of existing Javascript functionality.)</p>

<blockquote><h5>The first time I heard of D3, it was like, <br>&ldquo;oh wow. oh wow. oh. wow.&rdquo;</h5>

<p>It was exciting. It was tactile. It was beautiful sexy.</p></blockquote>

<p>Disclaimer: you&rsquo;re going to be much better off attempting this if you&rsquo;re comfortable with HTML, CSS, Vanilla (basic) Javascript, and at at least some understanding of DOM manipulation.</p>

<h3>5 steps in 5 minutes to get started:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Step 1 - <a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery">Go here</a> and copy the HTML and JSON of the file you like and save them each as their own files in the same local directory.  See my list of easy-to-use favs below.</li>
<li>Step 2 - Set up your local host - find the command you need <a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki#using">through this link</a>, then run that command in terminal when you&rsquo;re in the same local directory</li>
<li>Step 3 - in Chrome, navigate to the local host you&rsquo;ve opened. This will likely look something like <code>localhost:8888</code> in your search bar.</li>
<li>Step 4 - Tinker: see below.</li>
<li>Step 5 - Enjoy.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Fav beginner-level examples from the D3 site:</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062045">A cool force-directed Les Miserables character map</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4063550">A tree showing nested-layered info</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/280d83080497c8c13152">A fun particle thing</a></li>
</ul>


<h4>How to Tinker with the sample D3&rsquo;s from their site.</h4>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve got your example HTML file and JSON file in front of you, you&rsquo;re ready to see if you can prod this thing to make it jump. But to do that, you actually need to know a bit of D3 syntax.  Anywhere in your JS or HTML, when you see &ldquo;D3.[method]&rdquo;, that&rsquo;s essentially &ldquo;Document.[method]&rdquo;, having D3 methods called on it. Here&rsquo;s a shortlist for deciphering what you&rsquo;re reading:</p>

<p><code>selection.data</code> - This is the big boy. This is called the &ldquo;data join&rdquo; and it is the heart of how you incorporate your data set into the DOM. See more on data join basics <a href="http://bost.ocks.org/mike/bar/">halfway down this page</a>.</p>

<p><code>selection.attr(something)</code> - setting an attribute</p>

<p><code>selection.style(something)</code> - declaring the CSS-styling of the selection.</p>

<p><code>selection.property(something)</code> - imbuing the selection with a property (all these are well-named, no?)</p>

<ul>
<li>the 3 previous methods allow you to hard-code the &ldquo;something&rdquo; inside, but also to pass in a function that will dynamically generate that something depending on each data point. Syntax like so: <code>selection.text(function(d) { return d; });</code></li>
</ul>


<p><code>.domain(value1,value2)</code> - this is where you declare the domain of your data.</p>

<p><code>.range(value1, value2)</code> - and this is where you declare the range of pixels to which you want it to map.</p>

<h4>Enjoy.</h4>

<p>D3 allows us to create visualizations that are dynamic, that can easily change, that can update as often as the data that they visualize might.  It&rsquo;s a bit of a learning curve at the start (I&rsquo;m still on the curve), but so so pretty wow and worth it.</p>

<hr />

<h6>Further Resources:</h6>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/blog/2015/05/19/you-may-not-need-d3/">This guy</a> is great. He blogs about D3 often.</li>
<li><a href="http://color.method.ac/">Here&rsquo;s a great game to waste a lot of time</a> , built with D3. Thanks, D3.</li>
<li>Basically, <a href="http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock">all things mbostock</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When You Start a Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://eaud.github.io/blog/2015/12/02/when-you-start-a-blog/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-02T17:33:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://eaud.github.io/blog/2015/12/02/when-you-start-a-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It starts. And that&rsquo;s something.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
